Guide to the Joe Sitter Collection of Fine Printing, 1976-2015 and undated RL.11211
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joe Sitter collection of fine printing
1976-2015 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sitter, Joe
RL.11211
3.0 Linear Feet 3 boxes
Joe Sitter's collection of fine printing specimens and broadsides, as well as his subject files on various presses and artists.
Arrangement
Arranged into 2 series: Fine Printing and Subject Files.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Joe Sitter Collection of Fine Printing was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift and purchase in 2016.
Related Materials
The Rubenstein Library also holds the Joe Sitter Collection of Gaylord Schanelic.
Collection Overview
Broadsides, prints, and prospectuses from various fine press printers and artists; as well as subject files created by Sitter about various fine press printers and artists. Presses represented include The Whittington Press, Shanty Bay Press, Solmentes Press, and Ian Mortimer. Artists and printers represented are John Randle, Walter Bachinski, David Esselmont, Russell Maret, Howard Phipps, Miriam Macgregor, Hellmuth Weissenborn, and Judy Ling Wong.
Wood-engraving -- 20th century; Printing; Whittington Press; Sitter, Joe; Shanty Bay Press; Phipps, Howard; Weissenborn, Hellmuth; Macgregor, Miriam; Randle, John (Leslie John); Bachinski, Walter
- Fine Printing, 1976-2013; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Includes broadsides, prints, and prospectuses from various presses and artists collected by Joe Sitter. Some are numbered and signed by the artist. Illustrations are noted when identified.
  - Howard Phipps, 6
    - Morning Sunlight, Interior the Netherhall, 1982; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Matted color linocut, signed by Howard Phipps.
    - Catherine's Barn, 1988; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Catherine's Barn, undated; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Unmatted colored linocut, signed by Howard Phipps.
  - Shanty Bay Press, 4
    - Circus: The Artist as Saltimbanque, 2010; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Prints. 2 signed by Walter Bachinski.
  - Solmentes Press, 5
    - Blackberry, 2010 Oct. 14; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Print. Signed "for J.S. from D.E."
    - Flowerscape 2, 2010; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Print. Signed by David Esselmont.
    - Primula Auricula 3, undated; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Primula Auricula 1, undated; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ian Mortimer, 1
    - I.M. Imprimit, 1977; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Broadside
  - Swiss Cottage Library, 2
    - 28 Private Presses (Tribute to William Caxton), 1977; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Whittington Press, 3
    - Prescote Gallery exhibition, 1979; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Broadside. Illustrated with linocut by Juliet Caithness.
    - Eric Gill to the Dominicans at Hawkesyard Priory, Nov. 4th, 1917, 1982 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Broadside. Printed on Armatruda Amalfi handmade paper.
    - The Nightingale comes softly..., 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Broadside keepsake honoring the gift by Mr. and Mrs. Elmer L. Anderson of The Whittington Press Archive to the University of Minnesota.
    - Ebble Valley, 2007; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Broadside/prospectus. Illustrated with attached linocut and engraving by Howard Phipps.
    - Cheltenham Festival of Literature, 1980-1982; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Broadsides. Illustrated with wood engravings by Hellmuth Weissenborn.
    - Whittington: Memories of a Cotswold Village, by Frank Berry, 1982; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Broadsides. Illustrated with endpaper map, handcolored by Miriam Macgregor (2 versions: 1 colored; 1 not colored).
    - Whittington at Fullerton, printed for the Whittington Press Exhibition at Fullerton, California, 1984; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Broadside. Text and map excerpted from Whittington: Memories of a Cotswold Village. Handmade paper with watermark created by Henry Moore.
    - Whittington Summer Show, 1976, 1978-1982, 1984, 2001, 2009; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Broadsides. Illustrated with wood engravings by Hellmuth Weissenborn and Miriam Macgregor; 1 has a pochair by Miriam Macgregor.
    - Laura at Whittington, printed for the Summer Show., 1981; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Broadside. Illustrated with signed linocut by Howard Phipps.
    - Alphabets, printed for the Whittington Show, 1980; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Broadsides. Illustrated with wood engravings by Hellmuth Weissenborn. 2 versions.
    - Promotional posters re: printing An Alphabet on 1848 Columbian press, 1980; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Whittington Press exhibition, Special Collections, Wilson Library, University of Minnesota, 1984; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Broadside and brochure.
    - Blackwell's Rare Books booksale for Whittington Press, 1983; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Broadside. Illustrated with wood engraving by Hellmuth Weissenborn.
    - Whittington Press history, 1984; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Broadside. Illustrated with wood engraving of Manor Farm by Miriam Macgregor.
    - This is a Printing Office..., 1980 Jan.; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Broadside. Text by Beatrice Warde.
    - Fine Hand Printing/Bookbinding course advertisement, 1981; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Broadside. Created for Circencester Workshops.
    - Posters from Whittington, 1996-2013, 1 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Prospectus. Includes specimen with text from Hilary Pepler's The Hand Press. Wood engraving by Hellmuth Weissenborn.
    - Today I Lunched Off the Press at Whittington, 2011; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Broadside.
    - To the Displays of Dry Stone Walling and Typesetting, undated; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Invitation to an Illustrated Talk by John Randle, 1984; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Broadside, printed by Coffee House Press.
    - Keepsake for Art Libraries Society visit, 1980; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Exhibition at King Street Galleries, 1981; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Broadsides. 2 copies.
    - Birmingham Central Library exhibition, 1981; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Milton's Hymn: On the Morning of the Nativity, 1981; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Prospectus. Illustrated by William Blake. Published by D.H.E. Teesdale of Angscot Productions. 2 versions with different Blake specimens: The Old Dragon; The Annuciation to the Shepherds.
    - After the Funeral, by Paul Scott, 1979; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Prospectus. Illustrated by Sally Scott.
    - Harlequinade: 8 Mezzotints by Judy Ling Wong, 1979; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Prospectus. Illustrated with tipped in photolitho reproduction.
    - Iftikhar Azmi's The Garden of the Night, undated; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Prospectus.
    - Routes to Silence, by Lawrence Sail, 1978; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Broadside. Includes signature by Lawrence Sail.
    - London Types, undated; 13 items (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Prints.
    - An Almanac of 12 Sports, undated; 1 items (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Print.
    - An Alphabet, undated; 3 items (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minnesota Center for Book Arts
    - Handmade paper samples (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Subject Files, 1977-2015 and undated; 2
  Joe Sitter's Subject Files include an array of materials, including correspondence, from various presses and artists. The files were assembled by Sitter and also include original prints, prospectuses, and catalogs from some of the presses and artists. There are some duplicative materials between the Subject Files and the Fine Printing series.
  - Esselmont, David/Solmentes Press, undated (Box 3)
  - Fine Press Book Association, 2015 (Box 3)
  - Grolier Club, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Laughlin, James, 2014 (Box 3)
  - Macgregor, Miriam, undated (Box 3)
  - Maret, Russell, 2012-2014 (Box 3)
  - Old School Press, 2013 (Box 3)
  - Oxford Fine Press Book Fair, 2011 (Box 3)
  - Phipps, Howard, 1995-2007 (Box 3)
  - Rorer, Abigail/Lone Oak Press, 2007-2009 (Box 3)
  - Shanty Bay Press, 2010-2011 (Box 3)
  - Weissenborn, Hellmuth, 2012-2013 and undated (Box 3)
  - The Whittington Press: Catalogs, 1977-1995 (Box 3)
  - The Whittington Press: Correspondence, including with John Randle, 2008-2013 (Box 3)
  - The Whittington Press: Ephemera, undated (Box 3)
  - The Whittington Press: Portmeirion, 2008-2010 and undated (Box 3)